Okay,
בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today we wrap up today, last דף daf
or עמוד amud of מגילה, Megillah, we pick up today's דף daf
is ל"ב, lamed-bet, we pick up on the bottom of ל"א, lamed-aleph,
ל"ב, lamed-bet, and we pick up with... Okay, תניא, רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר אומר, Tanya Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar Omer... עזרא תיקן... Ezra tikken...
so the first word is the word
תיקן... tikken... it's about 14 lines from the bottom, give or take.
עזרא תיקן להם לישראל שיהיו קורין קללות שבתורת כהנים קודם עצרת... Ezra
tikken l'Am Yisrael sheyehu korin klalot shebeTorat Kohanim kodem Atzeret... Oh, we
did that. קללות שבמשנה תורה קודם ראש השנה. Klalot shebeMishneh Torah kodem
Rosh Hashanah. Excuse me, we're even further. תניא Tanya, רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר אומר... Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar Omer, line starts with the word
אומר... Omer... seven lines from the bottom. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר:
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer: אם יאמרו לך זקנים סתור וילדים בנה
סתור ואל תבנה... im yomru lecha zekenim setor veyeladim b'nei, setor v'al
tivneh... Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar says: if elders tell you to knock
down, to demolish,
and children tell you to build, to construct, סתור ואל תבנה, setor
v'al tivneh,
demolish and do not build. Listen to the elders, even if what
they are saying seems, you know, seems counterintuitive.
Or even against your...
Right, injudicious, sounds destructive. מפני שסתירת זקנים בנין ובנין נערים סתירה. mipnei
shestirat zekenim binyan, ubinyan nearim stirah. Because the destruction, the demolition of
elders, what they advise, ultimately will be constructive, and the construction of
youth ultimately will be destructive. וסימן לדבר, vesiman ladavar, so trust the
wisdom of your
elders, and the indication is רחבעם בן שלמה. Rechavam ben Shlomo. Oh
wow, Rechavam the son of Shlomo, as we know, you know, he
asked the elders what to do, and they said go light on
the people, and then the young people said, no, you do that,
they'll think you're a wimp, you gotta be harsh on them, so
he was harsh on them and it led to the entire splitting
of the land of Israel. Now, why we're exactly quoting this is
probably because we saw, said something earlier in רבי שמעון... Rabbi Shimon...
in yes, because we quoted a ברייתא Baraita before from רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. Okay, but that was apropos of
nothing. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Our Rabbis taught. מקום שמפסיקין בשבת שחרית
שם קורין במנחה. Makom shemapshikim b'Shabbat Shacharit, sham korin b'Mincha. The place
where you finish reading בשבת b'Shabbat in day, that's where you pick
up בשבת b'Shabbat afternoon, the next פרשה. parsha. במנחה, b'Mincha, where you
finish reading in מנחה, Mincha, שם קורין בשני. sham korin b'Sheni. That's
where you pick up on Monday. In case you didn't know that.
בשני, b'Sheni, where you finish reading on Monday, שם קורין בחמישי. sham
korin b'Chamishi. That's where you pick up on Thursday. ובחמישי, u'vChamishi, when
you finish on Thursday, שם קורין לשבת הבאה. sham korin l'Shabbat haba'ah.
That's where you read next שבת, Shabbat, דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi
Meir. So you see that? Makes your life a lot easier, you'll
only have to wind up doing like four עליות aliyos on שבת
Shabbat or you...
Well, that would... right, that would make it easier to get things...
Exactly! To get more people...
The problem is that not everybody gets to hear it. So that's
what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was a
סופר, sofer, I don't know if that has any relevance for this.
רבי יהודה אומר: Rabbi Yehuda omer: No. מקום שמפסיקין בשבת שחרית שם
קורין במנחה ובשני ובחמישי ולשבת הבאה. Makom shemapshikim b'Shabbat Shacharit, sham korin
b'Mincha u'v'Sheni u'v'Chamishi u'l'Shabbat haba'ah. So you be... where you left off
on the שבת, Shabbat, the next עליה, aliya, the first עליה aliya
of the next פרשה, parsha, is what you read שבת מנחה, Shabbat
Mincha, Monday, and Thursday, and that's what you start on שבת, Shabbat,
and that allows everybody to hear the reading on שבת Shabbat who
are not going to be there for those other times is presumably
the reason behind it. Also is why so many of us know
the first עליה aliya of all the פרשיות. parshiyot. Okay, so אמר
רבי זירא: Amar Rabbi Zeira: הלכה, halacha, and the הלכה halacha is:
מקום שמפסיקין בשבת שחרית שם קורין במנחה ובשני ובחמישי ולשבת הבאה. makom
shemapshikim b'Shabbat Shacharit, sham korin b'Mincha u'v'Sheni u'v'Chamishi u'l'Shabbat haba'ah. Like רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, where you left off on שבת, Shabbat, the next
עליה aliya you read again, you read it at שבת מנחה, Shabbat
Mincha, again on Monday, again on Thursday, and again on the following
שבת. Shabbat. ולימא הלכה כרבי יהודה? Dilayma halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda? So why
be so wordy? Why not just say the ruling is like רבי
יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? Top of ל"ב עמוד א'. lamed-bet amud aleph. משום
דאפכי להו, Mishum d'apchi lehu,
some people reverse which one רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, which one
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, so just so there should be no
confusion, he tells you the פסק הלכה, psak halacha, not the person
who says it. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Our Rabbis taught. פותח ורואה,
Poteach v'ro'eh, you open up the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, you see
where you're going to read from, גולל golel then you close it,
you scroll it up, ומברך u'mevarech and you say the ברכה, bracha,
וחוזר ופותח וקורא v'chozer u'poteach v'koreh and then you open it up
again and you read from it. Right, so a normal person now
gets an עליה, aliya, right, and they, you know, they get called
up, you know, the guy shows him, you know, the בעל קורא
ba'al koreh shows him, you look, you kiss or whatever, then you
close the תורה, Torah, you know, you make the ברכה, bracha, and
then you open the תורה Torah again and you read from it,
exactly as was described.
That's the אשכנז... Ashkenaz...
Well right... it could be ספרדי, Sephardi, you could look, close it...
According to the actual ספרדי פסק, Sephardi psak, is they're supposed to
keep it open.
Okay, well let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says,
but it could work with a ספרדי ספר תורה, Sephardi Sefer Torah,
no reason to have to... Okay, okay, so let's look what the
גמרא Gemara says. רבי יהודה אומר: Rabbi Yehuda omer: רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says, as Michael said, פותח ורואה ומברך וקורא. poteach v'ro'eh u'mevarech
v'koreh. You open, you see, you make the ברכה, bracha, then you
read. So, okay, so that at least makes sense, you're not having
a pause, you're not having extra closing,
you're not doing anything to interrupt the ברכה bracha in the beginning
of the reading. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda makes sense, right? Nice and
compact. Why should you do רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? So מאי טעמא
דרבי מאיר? Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Meir? What's the reasoning of רבי מאיר?
Rabbi Meir? כדיהו דעולא, Kidehu d'Ulla, like עולא Ulla said, דאמר עולא:
d'amar Ulla: מפני מה אמרו הקורא בתורה לא יסייע למתורגמן. mipnei ma
amru hakoreh baTorah lo yesaye'a l'meturgeman. The person reading the תורה Torah
should not help out the מתורגמן, meturgaman, right? The מתורגמן meturgaman is
like stumbling, he's trying to translate a word, and the guy the
בעל קורא ba'al koreh starts to like suggest a word to him,
you know, or fill in the blank for him. Why not? כדי
שלא יאמרו תרגום כתוב בתורה. kedei shelo yomru targum katuv baTorah. Because
if I'm the guy who's reading the תורה Torah and I'm saying
a few words for the תרגום, targum, people are going to think
I'm reading it from the תורה Torah and those words are written
in the תורה. Torah. So הכא נמי, hacha nami, here too. So
that's what עולא Ulla says, so apply the same reasoning here. Why
do we want to make sure it's closed when we make the
ברכה? bracha? כדי שלא יאמרו תרגום כתוב בתורה. kedei shelo yomru targum
katuv baTorah. So people... I'm sorry... כדי הכא נמי כדי שלא יאמרו
ברכות כתובות בתורה. kedei hacha nami kedei shelo yomru brachos ktuvos baTorah.
You want the תורה Torah closed when you when you make the
ברכה bracha so people should not say that the... you're reading the
ברכות brachos from within the ספר תורה. sefer Torah. Presumably the reason
you look at it beforehand is so that after you make the
ברכה bracha you'll know exactly where to go to, you know, you
won't have to hesitate looking around. Of course it happens all the
time that they reopen it and the... and the בעל קורא ba'al
koreh is again like where were we? Look at it looking around
again. But okay, hopefully there's less of that happening. It's sort of
like making the little cut in the חלה challah before you make
the ברכה bracha of the חלה. challah. Okay. So that's why we
do it. רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, what would רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
say back? תרגום איכא למטעי, targum ika l'michtei, the תרגום targum you'll
come to err. ברכות... brachos. because people might think, yeah, these words
are in... you know, written in the תורה. Torah. You know, there
is some ארמית Aramaic words in the תורה. Torah, It fits with
the narrative. That's a reasonable thing for people to mistake, and therefore
you want to be careful about that. ברכות ליכא למטעי. brachos leika
l'michtei. Nobody's going to think ברוך אתה ה' אלקינו מלך העולם אשר
קדשנו Baruch Atah Hashem Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam asher kideshanu is written in
the תורה, Torah? so you do not have to worry about that.
Because especially as every person has... gets an עליה, aliyah, it's like
having it repeated completely.
Right. Although in the time that... but for this ברייתא, braita, it
was only the first person and the last person, so it wouldn't
have been repeating itself. But nevertheless he said... but Michael is correct.
Nowadays it's even less of a concern because everybody's making ברכות. brachos
Who's really going to think it's written in the תורה? Torah So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבי זירא אמר רב מתנא הלכה והלכה
כפותח ורואה ומברך וקורא, Amar Rebbe Zeira amar Rav Matnah halachah v'halachah
k'poteach v'roeh u'mivarech v'koreh, like רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. You look... you
open it, you look, make the ברכה, bracha, you read, no interruptions.
So as Michael tells the ספרדי פסק. Sefardi psak. ולמה הלכה כרבי
יהודה, V'leimah halachah k'Rebbe Yehuda, why not to say we rule like
רבי יהודה? Rebbe Yehuda? משום דאחלופי... mishum d'achlufei... some people reverse which
is רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, which is רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, so
we want to state clearly what the פסק psak is. So that's
it, clear פסק הלכה. psak halachah. Why do we אשכנזים Ashkenazim or
ספרדים Sefardim do... why do we אשכנזים Ashkenazim do differently? So you
look at תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot says...
where is תוספות? Tosafot? The bottom of גולה לו. golelo. תוספות Tosafot
says like this.
He says like this.
ולכתחילה הוא גוללו וסותמו קודם שיברך כדי שלא יאמרו המון שהברכות כתובות
בו, U'lechatchilah hu golelo v'sotmo kodem sheyivarech kedei shelo yomru hamon shehabrachos
ktuvos bo, which is what the רבי מאיר's Rebbe Meir concern was.
אבל בדיעבד אין לחוש שהרי לא שכיחי עמי הארץ כל כך השתא.
Aval b'diavad ein lachush sheharei lo shchichi amei ha'aretz kol kach hashta.
That's לכתחילה, lechatchilah, but בדיעבד b'diavad you don't have to work... people
are not that ignorant that they're going to really think the ברכות
brachos, are written.
אבל אחר שקרא בו ודאי צריך לגוללו קודם שיברך, Aval achar shekara
bo vadai tzarich l'golelo kodem sheyivarech, אפילו כרבי יהודה, afilu k'Rebbe Yehuda,
the way they add it. But תוספות Tosafot says, but that's beforehand.
Afterwards you definitely have to close it. Why? Is there more of
a concern that the people are going to think the end ברכה
bracha is written than the beginning ברכה? bracha? Maybe not, but maybe
there's less of an issue of הפסק, hefsek, right? If the opening
ברכה, bracha, it's more like seemed like a ברכת המצוה birkat hamitzvah
or something, you know, you might want there to be like less
of a הפסק hefsek of the... of the reopening. Whereas by the
end, you know, it's less of a ברכת המצוה birkat hamitzvah so
it comes after, so the issues of הפסק hefsek are less. Or
maybe תוספות Tosafot actually thinks that somehow... I don't know... an opening
ברכה bracha people are more understanding that that's a ברכה, bracha, whereas
a closing ברכה bracha if people are less... you know, people expect
opening ברכות, so maybe somehow they more suspect that it's written in.
Anyway, what you see from תוספות Tosafot is that although the הלכה
halachah is you do it open and one might say it's דווקא,
davka, not that you're allowed to do it open. דווקא Davka you
do it open so there shouldn't be a הפסק, hefsek, תוספות Tosafot
actually in the end winds up being פוסקנינג paskening like רבי מאיר
Rebbe Meir at לכתחילה, lechatchilah, at least that's something to be concerned
about because he's concerned about more of a widespread ignorance, you know,
than apparently the גמרא Gemara felt it needed to be concerned about.
Yes.
Because sometimes the גמרא Gemara says uneducated people, you know what I
mean?
Right. Well, of course, and I was going to say, for ספרדים
Sefardim maybe that's less of a concern because ספרדים Sefardim are really
good at making sure everybody knows תורה Torah and תנ"ך. Tanakh. So,
you know, the קריאה, keriah, so maybe there's less of a concern
in that mistake. But again, Michael is correct, it is interesting and
at the same time תוספות Tosafot says people are really not that
ignorant, but he still wants you to be doing it לכתחילה. lechatchilah.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבי זירא אמר
רב מתנא. Amar Rebbe Zeira amar Rav Matnah. So since we had
a statement of רבי זירא Rebbe Zeira in the name of רב
מתנא Rav Matnah before, we have another statement in the name of
רבי זירא Rebbe Zeira in the name of רב מתנא. Rav Matnah.
So he says הלוחות והבימות אין בהם משום קדושה. Haluchos v'habimos ein
bahem mishum kedusha. A very sort of dense or opaque statement. The
literally the... the tablets and the... and the... and the...
not the balconies, what's a בימה? bimah? The daises, you know, the...
the... what do you call it? The dais, what else is it
called? A stand, a platform. Posts and the platforms don't have sanctity.
So what are the the you know the לוחות luchot and the
בימות, bimot, you know, what are these? So רש״י Rashi says, if
you take a look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says הלוחות, Haluchot,
רש״י Rashi says where are we?
Last wide line.
Last wide line, thank you. לא ידעתי מה הן. Lo yadati ma
hen. I don't know what these tablets are. ויש מפרשים הם העשויים
לספרים שלנו שאינם עשויים בגליון. ve-yesh mefarshim hem ha-asuyim li-sefarim she-lanu she-einam
asuyim be-gilyon. Maybe they are the blocks that block off a book.
You know, if you have a codex, the לוחות luchot are the
front and the back cover. Okay, so telling you אין בהם משום
קדושה ein bahem mishum kedusha although they're the covers of this codex,
you know, which raises then the question what is a codex? Does
that have קדושה kedusha if it's scribed, but it's not a scroll?
So it's interesting, but that's a good הווה אמינא hava amina then.
If the wraps of a ספר תורה Sefer Torah have קדושה, kedusha,
maybe the covers of a codex have קדושה. kedusha. So that's what
he suggests לוחות luchot means. And בימה, bima, the platform רש״י Rashi
says שהיו עושים למלך לפרשת המלך כדתנן במסכת סוטה. she-hayu osim la-melech
le-parshat ha-melech ke-detnan be-masechet Sotah. That's the closest רש״י Rashi was able
to come up to some בימה bima done for relating for קריאת
התורה. kriyat ha-Torah. So why all of a sudden we're dealing with
הקהל Hakhel once every seven years? But if you want to transform
it you could say if you read the Torah not just on
a on a platform, you know, on a we call that a
בימה, bima, right? But anyway, but read it not only on a
table, but the table is itself on a platform, so maybe that's
also connected to the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. So רש״י Rashi sees
this as things that are somehow connected to a Torah or to
a codex but not so closely connected and אין בהם משום קדושה.
ein bahem mishum kedusha. So assuming you had read this from I
mean we tend to have raised platforms, some of them are you
know part of the very structure of the floor, but some people
actually have a movable platform that they then get onto and read
the Torah from. So that's how רש״י Rashi reads it. תוספות Tosafot
and similarly רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel have a very different read. Look
at
תוספות. Tosafot. הלוחות והבימות אין בהם משום קדושה. Haluchot veha-bimot ein bahem
mishum kedusha. פירש בערוך גליוני ספר תורה שלמעלה ושלמטה ושל בין דף
לדף. peirush be-aruch gilyonei Sefer Torah she-lemala ve-she-lemata ve-she-bein daf le-daf. That
he says that this is figurative. If you have here your your
Torah scroll, right, and this is your white space, right, right, and
you have white space and you have white space here, right, and
you have white space here and you have white space here, right,
between each one of the columns. So these are לוחות. luchot. These
are like vertical tablets and this is a בימה, bima, right? This
is the platform. I mean, I don't know, that's a roof, but
okay, it's an upside down בימה. bima. Okay. So it means the
white space on the sides and on the top and the bottom
of the ספר תורה Sefer Torah don't have קדושה. kedusha. Then תוספות
Tosafot says but wait a minute, they do have קדושה. kedusha. Ah,
what the גמרא Gemara must be talking about is that if they
were cut away from the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, once they've been
cut away, אין בהם משום קדושה. ein bahem mishum kedusha. And that's
how תוספות Tosafot and רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel read it.
You know, you have to have like a five lines like that.
Right, so whether possibly ספר תורה Sefer Torah is another question and
you know but if but in terms of if you did cut
out the white space, let's say you were moving this דף daf
to another ספר תורה Sefer Torah whatever you were doing, if you
cut out the white margin once it's removed it does not have
משום קדושה. mishum kedusha. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר רב שפטיה אמר רבי יוחנן הגולל ספר תורה צריך שיעמידנו
על התפר. Amar Rav Shefatya amar Rabbi Yochanan ha-golel Sefer Torah tzarich
she-ya'amidenu al ha-tefer. The one rolling up the ספר תורה Sefer Torah
has to stand it, you know, has to sort of have the
the sewn part in the middle. When you roll it, you know,
sort of start, you know, the seam. Right. So you're rolling it
here, this has gotta be bad, I'm not anyway. Here's your like
scroll,
right, you know, this is like you know this is like your
right, this scroll here, as you're rolling it the seam between the
two pa- between the pages should sort of, you know, be in
the middle as you're tightening. Is that pretty clear?
As you're tightening it. Why? And also we also transfer this not
only to גולל golel but also to הגבהה. hagbaha. There's some discussion
that when in the גמרא Gemara when it's referring to גולל golel
it also means the one who's lifting it up and being גולל
golel it. But also because when you tighten it, right, if you
want to be pulling and the pressure at the seam. Why? You
say it'll tear. Yeah. But wouldn't you rather, right, let's say, you
know, wouldn't you rather your clothes rip at the seam or would
you rather they rip somewhere other than the seam? Right? So wouldn't
you rather if your ספר תורה Sefer Torah is going to rip,
it might be that that this will be a little bit weaker
than the middle of the דף daf but let let the pressure
be applied here so it'll tear at the seam, rather than the
pressure be applied somewhere else where it could actually rip the דף.
daf. Okay. Yes. So you're rolling it up when you roll you
pinch the roll which means you're tightening, right? So it's pulling pressure,
you know, away from the middle because the sides are being pulled.
And similarly when you lift it up.
Any time every
time you roll it up you should roll it up with the
seam down the middle.
And that makes it even harder to find where you left off.
You have to roll it up.
Oh, no. I don't think it means the light rolling on the
שולחן. shulchan. I think it means when you're tightening it, you know.
That's גולל golel low, right. The גמרא Gemara did use the word
גולל golel before. Use the word use the word oh, you're right,
it did use the word גולל. golel. But I think the assumption
here is when you're doing the tight tightening, not just at the
very
end.
Not just not you know roll it at the פרשה parsha that
you just
exactly, exactly, before you go or before or after
I don't know but that's also what we do with הגבהה hagbaha
as well because if you're talking about applying pressure when you do
הגבהה. hagbaha. heavy, you know, the poles are gonna pull like this
and you really I don't know, I've never heard of a case,
has anybody ever heard where the actual קלף klaf itself tore during
הגבהה? Hagbah? I've never heard of that. So okay.
James come... right, yeah.
All right, okay. So, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
ואמר רב שפתיא אמר רבי יוחנן, Va'amar Rav Shefatya amar Rabbi Yochanan,
says רב שפתיא Rav Shefatya in the name of
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, הגולל ספר תורה גוללו מבחוץ ואין גוללו מבפנים.
hagolel sefer Torah gollo mibachutz ve'ein gollo mibifnim. When you roll a
ספר תורה, sefer Torah, you do it on the outside and not
on the inside.
וכשהוא מהדקו מהדקו מבפנים ואינו מהדקו מבחוץ. ucheshehu mehadko mehadko mibifnim ve'eino
mehadko mibachutz. When you tighten it, you do it on the inside,
not the outside. What does this mean? So רש"י Rashi says what
it means is the following. רש"י Rashi says that you're there with
a, I should have brought some visual images, anyway, you're sitting down
and you've got the ספר תורה sefer Torah in your lap, and
you're a one-person job of moving, of you know, finding the right
place in the ספר תורה. sefer Torah. So it's usually easy with
two people, right? You put it on a table, you've got one
person holding, the other person rolling and you go nice and fast,
right? But let's say you don't have a table, you're one person
and you've got it all on your lap. Got to be a
pretty small ספר תורה. sefer Torah. So what are you going to
do? רש"י Rashi says what you want to be doing is, you
want to מבפנים mibifnim means close to you. So it
says, right, גוללו מבחוץ ואין גוללו מבפנים. gollo mibachutz ve'ein gollo mibifnim.
What you want to be doing is you've got it on your
lap, the part you want to be pulling towards, right, sort of,
you know, is away from you. So what you're going to do
is you'll take the bar that's, the poles that's away from you,
you know, you'll roll it up to close to you, the part
that sort of stays stable, stays close to your body, right, that
you're pulling the קלף klaf away from, and then you pull away
and then you do it again like this. So therefore you're in
control of the one that's farther from you so it doesn't get
away from you. But if you try to do the opposite, keep
the one far from you stable, right, and you want it to
roll like this, it's gonna fall over. Okay, so that's what that
means according to רש"י, Rashi, and וכשהוא מהדקו מהדקו מבפנים, ucheshehu mehadko
mehadko mibifnim, what רש"י Rashi says means is that when it's coming
time to finally, like, close, let me just double-check רש"י Rashi here
when he says
מהדקו. mehadko. Right, when you're done, you've found the right place and
now you want to close it up, he says in that case
you don't stretch your arm over the כתב ksav and close it
like this because then you're like covering the כתב. ksav. I don't,
it's hard for me to understand exactly, like I guess you're doing
it בציבור betzibur and you're not doing it ahead of time, and
he says you want people to be able to see the כתב.
ksav. So if you stretch your arm over and then you close
it that way, you're covering over the כתב, ksav, rather sort of
scroll it up the opposite way when you're finished after you're done
finding the right place, scroll it, you know, close it from the
inside to the out. תוספות Tosafot reads this very differently. תוספות Tosafot
reads it, he says what מהדקו mehadko is, based on what he
says מהדקו mehadko is you can figure out what גוללו gollo is.
מהדקו mehadko is when you put the, when you do the גארטל
gartel around the ספר תורה sefer Torah and you make the knot,
don't make the knot, מהדקו מבפנים, mehadko mibifnim, make the knot in
the front here and not in the back of the
ספר תורה.
sefer Torah. Why?
Well, only because it, you know, keeps it together better, but also
תוספות Tosafot says because next what's going to happen next time you
take out the ספר תורה? sefer Torah? If the knot is in
the back, you have to turn it upside down to undo the
knot. It's not כבוד kavod to the ספר תורה. sefer Torah. You
want to lie the תורה Torah, flat and have the knot right
in
front. That's מהדקו מבפנים. mehadko mibifnim. So גוללו מבחוץ gollo mibachutz for
him probably means what we do, when we do גולל, golel, you
stand behind, right, the guy stands back here, right, and he's rolling
it, right, and he's doing גולל golel it. He's not right in
front being גולל, golel, the guy sitting down is holding it, but
the guy behind being גולל, golel, presumably also so people could see
the כתב ksav as it's being scrolled up. So that's how תוספות
Tosafot understands what גוללו מבחוץ gollo mibachutz means. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, that's a much easier read than
רש"י. Rashi. ואמר רב שפתיא אמר רבי יוחנן עשרה שקראו בתורה, Va'amar
Rav Shefatya amar Rabbi Yochanan asara shekaru baTorah, ten people read the
תורה, Torah, which רש"י Rashi says does not mean ten people all
got עליה, aliyah, it means ten people gathered to read the
תורה, Torah הגדול שבהם גולל, hagadol shebahem golel, the greater one amongst
them gets גלילה. Gelila. גלילה Gelila is considered to be the biggest
honor. Now this is pretty funny, right, because in our שול shul
הגבהה וגלילה Hagbah u'Gelila are like what you give people that don't
merit a big עליה, aliyah, I shouldn't say that, but okay, for
everybody that's,
or for people that have the actual physical strength to do
הגבהה. Hagbah. Anyway, we don't treat it with that weight. Some people
say that again in the גמרא, Gemara, the גולל golel was actually
because you notice there's no discussion of the מגביה, magbi'ah, right, nowhere,
we haven't discussed הגבהה. Hagbah. So some people say that the גולל
golel in the גמרא Gemara was also the one who lifted it
and did the rolling, or maybe it works better with a ספרדי
ספר תורה, Sefardi sefer Torah, different ways of sort of figuring out
our contemporary ways of doing the scrolls and of doing הגבהה וגלילה.
Hagbah u'Gelila. So that the idea is the מגביה magbi'ah gets it,
and then it makes sense because then he gets to show the
ספר תורה sefer Torah to the people, right, and וזאת התורה, V'zos
haTorah, and then there's a power that that's also making about the
power of seeing something as opposed to hearing something, right, so if
you're actually the one who shows the תורה Torah. to the people.
that they've been hearing, you know, that's seen as like a very
special זכות zechut that you actually showed them the actual writing itself
and that really like, you know, made it really, you know, real
and resonate, resonate. So that's one way to understand it. רבינו חננאל
Rabbeinu Chananel if you take a look
says, רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel
says, where's רבינו
חננאל? Rabbeinu
Chananel?
Yes, the very first wide line. ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי עשרה
שקראו בתורה גולל ספר תורה לומר המשלים נותנין לו שכר כנגד כולם.
V'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi eser she-karu ba-Torah golel sefer Torah lomar
hamashlim notnin lo sachar k'neged kulam.
So he says the one who completes. So maybe it's somehow the
idea like, you know, like of the guy who goes last, he
gets credit for everything that came before him. אין מצווה נקראת אלא
על שם גומרה. Ain mitzvah nikret ela al shem gomrah. You know,
maybe he's also suggesting, although I don't know, I might want to,
you know, maybe I'm reading way too much into it, that the
guy who got the last עליה aliyah would naturally be the guy
who would do the גולל. golel. So maybe the המשלים hamashlim in
that sense. But somehow for him, the significance is just that you
are coming last. Okay, but I do think that there tends to
be an understanding that this is the person who lifted it up
and it's the power of showing it to people. Yes.
Does someone say you can have שביעי shvii or הגבה, hagba, you
should take הגבה? hagba?
Yeah, also if somebody says you should have שביעי shvii or מפטיר,
maftir, you should take שביעי shvii because but we, you know, what
we wind up sort of giving weight is different because מפטיר maftir
is considered also to be the least kavodik of the עליות aliyot
in the גמרא, gemara, but we wind up sort of giving, you
know, treating those things somewhat differently. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara
says like this.
So if there's like a חתן chasan that you should give them
or like a גרויסע רב, groyse rav, you should give them שביעי
shvii then instead of ששי shishi like we do, according to this,
right?
Well, if you read רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel that way, but that's
not clear. But at least you should give them הגבה hagba rather
than giving them ששי shishi which we don't do. Okay.
Where were we? Okay. כנגד
כולם. K'neged kulam. הגולל נוטל שכר כולם. Hagolel notel sachar kulam. Oh,
I think I forgot that
one
line. I just read ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי עשרה שקראו בתורה
הגדול שבהן גולל ספר תורה. V'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi eser she-karu
ba-Torah hagadol she-bahen golel sefer Torah. Why? Because
הגולל נוטל שכר כולם hagolel notel sachar kulam because he gets credit
for everybody that preceded him or equivalent of everyone who preceded him.
Okay, ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי. v'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. Did
I just, תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. עשרה שקראו בתורה הגדול שבהן גולל
ספר תורה קיבל שכר כולם. Eser she-karu ba-Torah hagadol she-bahen golel sefer
Torah kibel sachar kulam. He gets all of their credit. שכר כולם
סלקא דעתך? Sachar kulam salka dach-tacha? What? They don't get any credit,
he takes their credit away from them? So אלא אימא ela eima
you should say it קיבל שכר כנגד כולם, kibel sachar k'neged kulam,
equivalent to all of their
credit. Okay. ואמר רב שפטיה אמר רבי יוחנן. V'amar Rav Shefatya amar
Rabbi Yochanan. So that statement about the importance of גלילה gleila was
רב שפטיה בשם רבי יוחנן. Rav Shefatya b'shem Rabbi Yochanan. So another
statement of רב שפטיה בשם רבי יוחנן: Rav Shefatya b'shem Rabbi Yochanan:
מנין שמשתמשים בבת קול? minayin she-mishtamshin b'bas kol? Again, not exactly in
any, you know, any connection to the scene. How do you know
you're allowed to use a בת קול? bas kol? Now, right, now
what does that mean? רש"י Rashi says, אם בלבו לחתוך דבר ושמע
קול הן או לאו. im b'libo lach-to davar v'shama kol hen o
lav. If you were thinking should I go into this business deal
or not, should I invest in this stock or not, and then
you heard somebody say a loud voice said yes. So oh, okay,
so then אין כאן משום ניחוש, ein kan mishum nichush, that's not
considered some type of, you know, necromancy or divination. You're allowed to
actually use that as a סימן. siman. Okay, you know, like God,
please show me a sign. And then something actually happens. So somebody
says should I do it, should I not do it, and you
hear somebody yell yes. Oh, then you should use
it. שנאמר ואזניך תשמענה דבר מאחריך לאמר. Shene'emar v'aznecha tishmana davar mei-acharecha
leimor. Your ears will hear something from behind you telling you, telling
you what to do. והני מילי דשמע קול גברא במתא. V'hani milei
d'shama kol gavra b'mata. That's only if it's something unusual. Either it's
the sound of a person in the city in a place where
presumably, you know, guys would be out in the field at work,
it would be the women that would be left in the
town. או איתתא בדברא, o it-ta b'davra, or a woman's voice out
in the field where normally there would be only men. So it's
unusual. So then maybe it would be a סימן. siman. It would
not be something totally normal. Now again, does the גמרא gemara imagine,
it's always a question by בת קול, bas kol, you know, because
Saul Lieberman shows that בת קול bas kol originally did not mean
a heavenly voice, it meant like a, a report went down, you
know, a שמועה. shmuah. So here does בת קול bas kol mean
that you're hearing some type of a disembodied heavenly voice, and the
reason that it should be a man's voice in the city or
a woman's voice in the field is to know that it's not
really a person's voice at all? Or is it no, you did
hear somebody just yell yes, like, you know, they were talking to
their friend and they yelled out a big yes. So it is
a person's voice, but nevertheless if it's unusual, then it's a סימן.
siman. If it's not unusual, it's not a סימן. siman. So again,
it's not clear that the גמרא gemara imagines that this is actually
a heavenly voice. It's some type of a sound that you heard
and a voice that you heard. Maybe it is human but it's
unusual. Okay, והוא דאמר הין הין והוא דאמר לאו לאו. V'hu d'amar
hin hin v'hu d'amar lav lav. And it's not just enough that
you heard a voice say yes. It has to be yes, yes,
or no, no. That should be your סימן. siman. Okay, and then
you can use it. Now if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות
Tosafot says like this: מנין שמשתמשים בבת קול, minayin she-mishtamshin b'bas kol,
בירושלמי. b'Yerushalmi. because it says
תני, tani, כתיב ksiv לא תנחשו ולא תעוננו, lo senachashu v'lo se'onenu,
do not do divination and do not, like, look in the stars
or whatever, אף על פי שאין ניחוש, af al pi she'ein nichush,
even though you can't do divination, יש סימן, yesh siman, you can
still use hints. Quite funny, reminds me of a joke. Somebody goes
into his, he's got a friend who's a doctor, he goes into
his office and he sees that he's got one of these, like,
what are they, חמסות khamsas up, you know? So he says to
him, he says "I don't understand you," he says, "You are a
man of science, you're such a rational
man, what are you doing with
this superstitious thing up in your office?" He says, he says "I
heard that even for people who don't believe in it, it still
works." So anyway,
alright, so the גמרא Gemara says, alright, so, okay. ואמר רב שפטיא
אמר רבי יוחנן, v'amar Rav Shfatya amar Rabbi Yochanan, another
statement of רב שפטיא Rav Shfatya in
the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, back to closer to our
theme. כל הקורא בלא נעימה, kol hakoreh belo ne'imah, if you read
the Torah without trop, והשונה בלא זמרה, v'hashoneh belo zimrah, or you
learn the משניות mishnayos without a without a ניגון, nigun, right? Because
they would learn it in a sing-song, in a type of a
ניגון, nigun, because it's easier to remember it that way. Right? You
look at תוספות, Tosfos, השונה בלא זמרה, hashoneh belo zimrah, שהיו רגילים
לשנות המשניות, shehayu regilim lishnos hamishnayos, specifically שונה, shoneh, it's not learning
of גמרא, Gemara, but it's memorizing
in an oral culture. בזמרה לפי שהיו שונים אותם על פה ועל
ידי כך היו נזכרים יותר. bezimrah lefi shehayu shonim osam al peh
v'al yedai kach hayu nizkarim yoser. Like and you, somebody who, earlier
in life, you used to be a בעל קורא, ba'al koreh, used
to read a lot from the Torah—I wasn't a בעל קורא, ba'al
koreh, but I used to read a lot from the Torah—anything I
learned with the trop I remember. You know, so it's totally true.
So anyway, so if you learn it without the trop, which a)
not only means that you won't remember it, it's not so bad
for the גמרא Gemara not to have the Torah memorized because דברים
שבכתב אי אתה רשאי לאומרם בעל פה, devarim shebiksav i ata rashai
le'omram ba'al peh, but the trop helps you know where to put
the punctuation, right, how to divide up the פסוק, pasuk, or you
learn the משנה mishnah without the זמרה, zimrah, without the singing, and
you're not going to remember it well. עליו הכתוב אומר, alav hakasuv
omer, for regarding him the verse says, וגם אני נתתי להם חוקים
לא טובים, vegam ani nasati lahem chukim lo tovim, okay, ומשפטים לא
יחיו בהם. umishpatim lo yichyu bahem. I have given them edicts that
were not good and laws that they shall not live by. Very
difficult פסוק, pasuk, but it means I have given them חוקים chukim
and they have made them לא טובים lo tovim because they have
not held onto them in the proper way.
It's clearly reading it as a מכה, makkah, otherwise it would have
said "it by us".
Okay, right, but it's obviously not good.
Although again the גמרא Gemara doesn't specifically say it's about remembering, and
it uses the term נעימה ne'imah for reading and the the אסמכתא,
asmachta, the proof text, would indicate that it's to make it, to
make it sound good. I'm sure you've heard plenty of
בעל קריאות ba'al kria's
who were very precise...
Right, that's a good point... but they didn't have a lot of
נעימה. ne'imah. Exactly. So where do you see that from the proof
text?
נעימה, ne'imah, meaning it's not like...
No I get, oh the נעימה, ne'imah, but I mean from the
פסוק pasuk of ומשפטים... umishpatim... Oh, it's not good, it's not pleasant,
I see, okay, interesting. Okay, although again I do think there is
a difference between the משנה mishnah which is about memory and the
Torah. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, מתקיף לה אביי, maskif lah
Abaye, אביי Abaye asked on this, משום דלא ידעי לבסומי קליה, mishum
d'lo yadai l'vasumei kalei, so he, אביי Abaye understands like Dove. What,
just because you don't have a nice voice, so it doesn't talk
about memory or precision, just because you don't have a nice voice
ומשפטים לא יחיו בהם קרית ביה? umishpatim lo yichyu bahem kris bi?
You're going to say laws that you will not live by? Meaning
it's one thing to say לא טובים lo tovim like Dove said,
it's not so pleasant to hear people with a bad voice, but
ומשפטים לא יחיו בהם? umishpatim lo yichyu bahem? אלא כרב משרשיא, ela
k'Rav Masharshiya, it's like רב משרשיא, Rav Masharshiya, דאמר d'amar who says,
שני תלמידי חכמים היושבים בעיר אחת, shnei talmidei chachamim hayoshvim b'ir achas,
two Torah scholars that are sitting in one city ואין נוחים זה
לזה בהלכה v'ein nochim zeh lazeh b'halacha and are not sort of
pleasant to one another בהלכה, b'halacha, which could, which is a little
vague what it means. The מהרש"א Maharsha means that it means that
they don't discuss הלכה halacha together, they learn by
themselves, they don't sort of show respect to one another and they
don't discuss and and there's no חברותא, chavrusa, they're just each one
is off by their own. So that case, how's it translate there
in the English, "v'ein nochim zeh bazeh"? Does it say anything? Not
pleasant to one another?
Cooperate with one another in discussing matters of law.
Okay, so it says it reads it like the מהרש"א. Maharsha. Okay,
so anyway, ואין נוחים זה בזה בהלכה. v'ein nochim zeh bazeh b'halacha.
So in that case עליהם הכתוב אומר, alehem hakasuv omer, וגם אני
נתתי להם חוקים לא טובים ומשפטים לא יחיו בהם. vegam ani nasati
lahem chukim lo tovim umishpatim lo yichyu bahem. Because now you could
really say לא יחיו בהם lo yichyu bahem because the laws will
not be precise and proper and they'll pervert the law. The laws
will wind up being perverted because you do not, unless you get
pushback and critique and discussion, you do not get to the right
conclusion. אמר רב פרנך אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rav Parnach amar Rabbi
Yochanan, and it also fits in with other גמרות, gemaros, you know,
that says חרב אל הבדים
ונואלו. cherev el habadim v'no'alu. Right, exactly, a sword against those who
would learn by themselves and not learn בחברותא b'chavrusa and so on.
Okay, אמר רב פרנך אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rav Parnach amar Rabbi
Yochanan, כל האוחז ספר תורה ערום, kol ha'ochez sefer torah arom, anybody
who holds onto a ספר תורה sefer torah naked, which means that
the ספר תורה sefer torah is naked, it's not you're not sort
of you're touching the cloth. yourself, you're not
handling it
through the cover or through the poles, through the
עצי חיים. atzei chayim. So נקבר ערום, nikbar arom, you're buried naked.
ערום סלקא דעתך Arom salka da'atchach really?
Such a bad sin that you would be buried without shrouds? אלא
אימא נקבר ערום בלא מצוות. Ella eima nikbar arom belo mitzvos. Fine,
stripped of all mitzvos. That's better. בלא מצוות סלקא דעתך? Belo mitzvos
salka da'atchach? What, you're stripped of all mitzvos? אלא אמר אביי נקבר
ערום בלא אותה מצוה. Ella amar Abaye nikbar arom belo osah mitzvah.
You don't get שכר schar for that מצוה. mitzvah. What's that mean?
תוספות Tosfos says, that's pretty obvious, right? I mean, if you did
the מצוה mitzvah wrong, you shouldn't get שכר schar for it. So
if you look at תוספות, Tosfos, it says בלא אותה מצוה, belo
osah mitzvah, says תוספות, Tosfos, יש מפרשים מצות אחיזה. yesh mefarshim mitzvas
achizah. You don't get the מצוה mitzvah for holding the ספר תורה
Sefer Torah or being גולל golel it or whatever you were doing
when you were touching it. וקשה מאי רבותא פשיטא שאין לו שכר
כיון שלא עשה מצוה כהוגן. Vekasha mai revusa peshita she'ein lo schar
keivan shelo asah mitzvah kehogen. לכך פירש ריב"א בלא אותה מצוה שעשה
באותה שעה. Lekach peirash Riva belo osah mitzvah she'asah be'osah sha'ah. You
don't get credit for any other
מצוה mitzvah you would be doing in the context of holding it.
כגון שאם אחז ספר תורה ערום וקרא בו, Kegon she'im achaz Sefer
Torah arom vekara bo, if you were holding on directly on the
קלף klaf and reading it, אין לו שכר מן הקריאה. ein lo
schar min hakriya. You don't get benefit, you don't get the merit
of reading the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. It undermines the מצוה mitzvah
of reading because the holding of it was done improperly. So not
only does it undermine the merit of holding the ספר תורה, Sefer
Torah, it undermines the merit of whatever else was done in that
context. Okay, and similarly if you did גלילה gelilah that way, you
don't get שכר schar for גלילה, gelilah, etc. Okay, back to the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבי ינאי בריה דרבי ינאי סבא, Amar Rabbi Yannai
breih deRabbi Yannai Saba, Rabbi Yannai the son of Rabbi Yannai the
elder. So here you see already like the ספרדי Sefardi מנהג minhag
of children with the same name as the father. משמיה דרבי ינאי
רבה, Mishmei deRabbi Yannai Rabbah, and Rabbi Yannai was the grandfather, so
this was a grandfather, father, and son all with the same name.
מוטב שיגולל המטפחות ואל יגולל ספר תורה. Mutav sheyigollel hamatpachos ve'al yigollel
Sefer Torah. Better to roll up, you know, with the מטפחות matpachos
rather than to roll the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. Not exactly clear
what that means.
רש"י Rashi says it means, if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י
Rashi says, ואל יגול ספר תורה בתוך המטפחת. Ve'al yigol Sefer Torah
betoch hamatpachas. So first roll the ספר תורה Sefer Torah before you
put on the cover and then put the cover on. Don't put
the cover and then do the tightening after the cover's already on.
Last line. וידבר משה את מעדי ה' אל בני ישראל. Vayedabber Moshe
es mo'adei Hashem el Bnei Yisrael. מצותן שיהיו קוראים אותן כל אחד
ואחד בזמנו. Mitzvosan sheyihyu korim osan kol echad ve'echad bizmano. This is
the basis that we get for reading every
פרשה, parsha, every מועד, moed, the appropriate פרשה parsha in the תורה.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught, משה תיקן להם לישראל שיהיו
שואלים ודורשים בענינו של יום. Moshe tikken lahem leYisrael sheyihyu sho'alim vedorshim
be'inyano shel yom. Not only about reading the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah,
Moshe established that we should learn the laws of the, notice,
not קוראים, korim, but שואלים ודורשים, sho'alim vedorshim, right? So learning the
laws, הלכות פסח בפסח הלכות עצרת בעצרת הלכות חג בחג, Hilchos Pesach
bePesach, Hilchos Atzeres beAtzeres, Hilchos Chag beChag, each one in the proper
time. Of course, there's another statement of שלושים יום shloshim yom before,
but okay, there's some things that you need to prepare for and
do שלושים יום shloshim yom before and you need time to really
learn the הלכות. halachos. And then there's actually an idea why I
would say not just in terms of knowing what to do, that's
more the teaching of שלושים יום קודם החג, shloshim yom kodem hachag,
but more in terms of embracing the nature of the day through
the learning of the הלכות halachos of the day in a more
sort of almost ritual sense. Not you should learn the הלכות halachos
because you don't know what you're doing tonight for the סדר. Seder.
You learn the הלכות halachos because that's what you do on פסח,
Pesach, if you learn הלכות פסח. Hilchos Pesach. It's a way of
being מקיים mekayem the nature of פסח. Pesach. And I think it's
significant that, and I think it's subtle, but notice what the גמרא
Gemara did here in the last line, right? We had an entire
פרק, perek, one might say an almost מסכת, masechet, about the importance
of scripture, right? About the reading of the מגילה, Megillah, the בית
כנסת, Beis Knesses, the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, the קריאה, kriya, all
of this. Right? We even had at the beginning, מבטלין mevatlin what
for the sake of קריאת מגילה? kriyas Megillah? תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah
for the sake of מקרא מגילה. Mikra Megillah. Right? And here at
the very end, when we end with saying that you read from
the ספר תורה Sefer Torah of the nature of the יום טוב,
Yom Tov, we end with the line that you know what you
do on the יום טוב? Yom Tov? You learn the הלכות. halachos.
You learn Torah. Not you read from the Torah, but it's the
תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah that you do relating to the יום טוב.
Yom Tov. And again getting back to that obviously more dominant רבני
rabbinic theme. Just to show how both רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos
like to end on a nice little
flourish, take a look at רש"י Rashi says, הלכות,
רש"י Rashi says, למה הוצרך לכתוב, Lama hutzrach lichtov, he explains what
we learn it from the פסוק. pasuk. Why did it have to
say וידבר משה? Vayedabber Moshe? וכי כל המצות כולן לא אמרן משה
לישראל? Vechi kol hamitzvos kullan lo amran Moshe leYisrael? מהו וידבר משה
את מעדי ה' אל בני ישראל? Mahhu Vayedabber Moshe es mo'adei Hashem
el Bnei Yisrael? So he's explaining where we get this from the
verse because וידבר Vayedabber is superfluous. ללמד שהיה מדבר עמהם הלכות כל
מועד ומועד בזמנו. Lelammed shehayah medabber immahem hilchos kol mo'ed umo'ed bizmano.
Now again it's הלכות. halachos. Right? We're now at the last line
of the גמרא, Gemara, not just to be קורא, korei, but the
הלכות halachos of each one in its right time. בזמנם ולהודיע חוקי
האלוהים ותורותיו, Bizmanam ulehodia chukkei ha'Elokim vesorosav, to tell people the laws
and the teachings. וקבלו וקיימו שכר המצוה, Vekibbelu vekiyemu schar hamitzvah, one
wonders it's because it's the end of מגילה, Megillah, so there's a
little קבלו וקימו שכר המצוה עליהם ועל בניהם בזה ובבא, kibbelu vekiyemu
schar hamitzvah aleihem ve'al beneihem baze uvava, and they accepted it on
them and their future and for all future generations. That clearly was
a little flourish, which we got because it was the end of
a מסכת. masechet. Similarly...
Right, exactly, exactly. And also in תוספות, Tosafot, the one we read
before about בלא אותה מצווה Belo Otah Mitzvah ends with a little
flourish. תוספות Tosafot says,
אבל אחד המטפחות, Aval Echad Hametpachot, but if somebody is not, doesn't
touch the קלף Klaf directly, last two lines of תוספות, Tosafot, but
does it through the קלף, Klaf, you know, through the wrappings, אורך
ימים בימינה, Orech Yamim Bimina, בשמאלה עושר וכבוד. Bismola Osher Vachavod. Okay,
very nice ending. So, what? He knew how to do a סיום.
Siyum. Okay, הדרן עלך, Hadran Alach, והדרך עלן, V'Hadrach Alan, מסכת מגילה.
Masechet Megillah. Okay, so, so let's do the סיום. Siyum. Just turn
this off and we'll do the סיום. Siyum. Okay, שקויח. Shkoach.